A Guide to the Papers of the Barney, Cooke, McClew and Neilson families, 1820-1905
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Barney, Cooke, McClew and Neilson families, 1820-1905
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7786-x
There are 175 items in this collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of Bruce Engstler, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1996 April 17.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists mainly of letters, 1865-1875, between Charles D. Barney and Laura E. Cooke, daughter of financier Jay Cooke. Barney, writing chiefly from Sandusky, Ohio and Philadelphia, Pa., discusses their love and future marriage; religious beliefs, church services and sermons; family and friends; social events particularly games, rides, concerts, and dances, as well as a mass meeting addressed by B. F. Wade, a reading by Harriet E. Kimball, and a veterans' parade in Philadelphia.
He describes the ruins of the Chicago fire and briefly notes work in the firm of Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers. People mentioned include Wiliam W. Newton, Jay Cooke, Jay Cooke, Jr., and William White Harding.
Letters of Laura Cook to Barney discuss her love for him; her family and social life; reading; wedding plans, and travels including trips to Kentucky, the grand falls of the Potomac, Fall River, Mass., Newport, R.I., Michigan, Cape May, N.J., Gibraltar and Sandusky, Ohio, She notes church attendance and sermons or services by Alfred Lee, Henry Ward Beecher, John Philip Newman, Charles Edward Cheney and Heman Dyer.
There are comments on the Presidential election of 1868, travel on the steamer "Jay Cooke, " her father's fishing, and family productions of "Cricket on the hearth." There are very brief mentions of Julia Grant, Hugh Lenox Bond, Benjamin Butler, Lewis B. Gunckel, and John H. Martindale.
The collection also contains a programme for an 1868 performance of "Drummer Boy!" in Sandusky, Ohio, annotated with notes on the performance [by Laura Cooke?]
Letters to Barney and Cooke from family and friends include a letter from Harry E. Cooke, traveling in Italy in 1869; a letter from Jay Cooke arranging a position in his firm for Barney; and a letter from Charles B. Dennis, Office Mustering Dept., 4th Army Corps, Chattanooga, 1864 July 13, giving news of friends briefly mentioning Charles Cruft, General Jefferson C. Davis, Charles G. Harker, John D. Imboden, [Isaac Minor?] Kirby, John I. Morrison, Lew Wallace, and Kenesaw Mountain.
The letters also contain letters to emigrant Charles McClew of Montgomery County, N.Y. from relatives in Scotland, 1822-1940, conveying news of family and friends. Topics include college life in Glasgow, economic distress, and religious unrest.
Miscellaneous correspondence unrelated to the rest of the collection includes: an 1841 letter describing a visit to Richmond, Va., by William Henry Harrison and John Tyler that also mentions Thomas Ritchie and Thomas Walker Gilmer; an 1889 letter from Bloomingburgh, N.Y. concerning rowing, fishing, and hunting; 1890 correspondence of Alfred Kean Moe, Jersey City, concerning a student who had dropped out of school; and a 1904 letter from an unknown University of Virginia student concerning James B. Green, a blind tutor at the U. Va. School of Law, Betty Burwell Page Cocke, Betty Page Cocke, and "Raleigh" the Cocke's servant at their boarding house.
Contents List
- I. LETTERS FROM CHARLES D. BARNEY TO LAURA E. COOKE
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1865 Oct 22
    Sandusky, Ohio: church services; a 'Negro "Minstral"'; social affairs such as parties and dances; family
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1866 Oct 3
    Sandusky, Ohio: Mr. Ingersoll's beautiful discourse on repentance; scripture quotes; visit to Camptown Chapel; the Fair; expresses love for her
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1866 Nov 11
    Sandusky, Ohio: on sharing thoughts with her, such as truths of the "beautiful parable of the Prodigal Son"; sermon of Mr. Farr; scripture quotes; lengthy description of a performance of scenes -- "Rose fete" with comments on Clara, Lollie Mills, Connie Homer, Essie Mills, Frank Butler, Sophie Fitzhugh, Hannah, Jake Homer, Mary Osborne, and his namesake Charlie Johnson, "a little colored boy," and others; including Sallie Graham, Emma Marsh, Kitty Campbell, Emma Moss, George Maxwell, Lena Mills, Sallie Mills; "Taking the Oath"; "Ring of Cashiers," specifically "The Rose," with comments on Mary Osborne, Emma Marsh, Sallie Graham, Jessie Stern, and Clara; "The Dentistry Establishment," "Rustic Courtship," "Intercepted Letter," "The Belle of Orleans," "Rock of Ages," and "Mistletoe Bough" (scenes? from the "history of the great Sandusky sensations of 1866")
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1866 Dec 5
    Sandusky, Ohio: parochial meeting; religious thought; poem to Longellow's "Waif"; comments on the temperament of a tailor and on having a tailor as a president [Andrew Johnson (1808-1875)]; longing for them to be together in marriage
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1866 Dec 9
    Sandusky, Ohio: comments on the church sermon on the coming of the Lord by Mr. Farr; religious thoughts and trust in God; Dr. Bancroft, professor at the Theological Seminary at Gambier; her distrust of reverends and his thoughts of becoming one
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Jan 4
    Sandusky, Ohio: thankful to God for having her in his life; missing a gathering at Hannah's with Mary Radcliff, Ella Higgins, and Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; skating at Cedar Point; comments on writing in the fashion of Victor Hugo
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Jan 30
    At home: reassures her of his devotion to her; a gathering at the Latham's with the Misses Robertson, Latham, and Barney (Ella and Sallie) singing compositions of Mozart, Farmer, and Mercidanti; Mr. Farr
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Mar 13
    Sandusky, Ohio: Clara; a journey of Clara and Laura on Chestnut Street; thoughts on Laura's falling in love with various girls -- as a "Christian charity among the quieter sex"; Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; remembrance of a gift of a rosebud to her; marriage of Mary Osborne to a gentleman from Louisville, Kentucky; quiet Lenten season with services and lectures by Mr. Farr
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Mar 31
    Sandusky, Ohio: went to the Fair; prizes won by Allie Porter, Nettie Watherell, Clara, Sallie Reber, Mr. Reber, Charlie Bouton, and the G.A.R. Society
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Apr 20
    Sandusky, Ohio: thoughts of the coming June (the time of their marriage) for happiness; remembers their delightful talks and the happiness of their 'short & sweet' association; description of visit to Central Park and Broadway; visit to Laura's brother Pitt Cooke and Willie Pritchard in Brooklyn and a trip to 'Fulton Market' with them; visit to Aunt Mary's with Hal, Willie Pritchard, Mrs. Pitt, Mrs. Pritchard, and Townie Pritchard; heard Maggie Mitchell that evening; railroad and ferry rides home to Sandusky; church attendance with Mr. Farr and Jay Butler -- describes Easter service; singing the hymn; [ ] Farr's sermon; news of their engagement out
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Apr 22
    Sandusky, Ohio: trust in God, in her, and the future; discussion of patterns; Charles Olds; Jay Butler; Emma Marsh; Kitty Campbell; Luke Mills; Jay and Clara Moorehead; "Fort Whipple," Virginia where he was a Corporal in the 100 Days War
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 May 1
    At home: patterns of animals for his mother's afghan; business getting brisk; description of scenery around Washington, D. C.; Laura's opal being found; comments on her performance of "The Cricket on the Hearth"; "Grand Army and Union League meetings; Charles Augustus; Hannah Marshall
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 June 5
    Sandusky, Ohio: playing charades; arrangements for a concert with assistance from Mr. Andersen, Sallie Mills, and Sally Reber
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 June 6
    Sandusky, Ohio: reminsces about their first meeting two years previous; arrangements for the concert and rehearsal that night
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 June 27
    Sandusky, Ohio: in appreciation of her kindnesses; loving letter, expressing his feelings of love; Mrs. Barney, Ella, Sallie, "Grandma," [Jay Cooke], and Uncle Collie playing backgammon; ride and dance following night with Cora Brown; cancelled trip to the island, going to School Exhibition with his mother instead; Jay Butler; Martha Cooke; Lake Mills
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Aug 2
    Sandusky, Ohio: joy in receiving her letter; Georgia Moss; Jay Butler; conversation on housekeeping; their engagement; photograph of her carriage enclosed; romantic thoughts; a river adventure braved by Sallie [Cooke] and Laura; Martha Cooke
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Aug 17
    Gibraltar, Put-In-Bay: Clara Hepburn; boat ride to "Gibraltar, Put-In-Bay," boat ride around the bay; playing croquet; prayers and sermon conducted by Mr.Taylor; bay ride during which a German man with an accordion entertained; description of the water, air, and moonlight -- the atmosphere -- of the bay ride; Dr. [Thomas Hewlings?] Stockton (1808-1868) suffering and thoughts concerning this matter; Sunday church prayers by Mr. Peck; humorous comment on his musical aptitude in comparison to George Morgan; description of activities and music from the steamers by the wharf; romantic thoughts
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Sep 12
    Sandusky, Ohio: attended mass meeting held in the [South Mansfield Station] and Newark Railroad Passing Depot which was addressed by Benjamin [Franklin] Wade and N. C. McFarland; Aunt Martha [Cooke]; proceedings of last night's meeting during which he was chosen secretary
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Sep 15
    Sandusky, Ohio: Aunt Martha [Cooke]; cousin Dora and Aunt Sarah [Moorhead?] train trip to Sandusky; Lake Mills; visit to Aunt Caldwell's
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Sep 18
    Sandusky, Ohio: religious overtones concerning their love and relationship; Lake Mills; Jake Hosmer; lottery drawings for prizes; Fishers Hall a gambling hole; sermons from Dr. Bancroft and Mr. Fullerton, Presbyterian minister; vote of township ticket; Kittie Campbell; Theo Hosmer; the Fair; George Thomas lecture on 'Sign boards'; her report of the Japanese visit to her [incomplete letter]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1867 Oct 18
    Sandusky, Ohio: Jay [Cooke, Jr.] and Clara; "closed up entirely at the Bank so that now I am through -- there forever -- I guess -- I must make a few more calls this P. M. & then I shall be out of that business & entirely a man of ease without a thing in the world on my hands --"; visit to Mrs. George Anderson on her fifteenth wedding anniversary
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke [1867 Oct?]
    The Office: planning a trip to Cleveland, Ohio and offers to pick up Laura if she is coming through
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke [1867 Oct?]
    --: reading [The Chronicles of the] Schonberg-Cotta Family[by Elizabeth Rundle Charles], commenting on it as "the most useful -- truthful -- interesting & simply beautiful book" he ever read; determined to meet Laura in Cleveland, Ohio; Miss Horstman; an evening dancing party; big fire consumed the Marsh's Plaster Mill; choir singing in church; Mr. Farr of the church; his own successor in the office
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Mar 11
    Ogontz "Library," [Chelten Hills, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]: choir meeting; stories of Mr. Rickerts; notes from Nennie and John M. Bronaugh, Sallie [Cooke], H. A. Rickert with a sketch; locks of hair
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 May 27
    Ogontz 'Chinese' Room: Kittie Tryvilian; Jim Bingham; [Jay Cooke] her father at the office and home; [John W.] Sexton, George [Thomas]; Mr. Rickert playing piano in the parlor; Della Coles; describes drive in the buggy with the Cooke family; drowning of local boy, the son of Isiaah Drain, in the Penn Mill Creek; playing billiards; Mr. and Mrs. Appleton, Mr. and Mrs. Thomas, Willie Newton, Mr. and Mrs. Parvins all at house; Jay Cooke conducted private business conversations at house; prayers and hymns; ride in the "Omnibus"
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 May 28
    The Office: Laura in Detroit, Michigan; [Jay Cooke], Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; George [Thomas], Willie Newton, Mr. Rickert on train together; doctrinal discussion on "Stubbs & Boggs" [incomplete letter]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 May 29
    --: Harry Bingham: Mrs. Barney's afflicted state; John at Ida and Ginnie Thomas'; reading by Miss [Harriet McEwen] Kimball (1834-1917) of [Friedrich] Schiller's Mary Stuart; visit to Birdsells for strawberries and cream; moving to new quarters on 9th Street at the Aldens; Eckstein Nagle & Company; spending the weekend at Ogontz with Mr. Bingham, John, Willie Newton [Note: William Wilberforce Newton (1843-1914) married Emily Stevenson Cooke on November 16, 1870, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], and Mr. Rickert
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 May 31
    Ogontz "Chinese room": discussion of a conversation on women by Mr. Bingham, John, and himself; Willie Newton; Miss Horstman; playing billiards; activities at Ogontz; Richard Thomas; Mr. Appleton; Mr. Rickert; Mr. Parvins; Emma Faris; Sunday school and church services; "poney carriage" ride to Branchtown; Maimie Brock
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 [May?]
    Ogontz "Chinese room": describes horseback ride on "Miss 'Kitten'" with Tom -- saw the Brocks, "Rockwood," the Parvins, and the Gimps; dinner at the Continental; piano and flute performance by Charlie and Tom; religious thoughts; new lodgings at Mrs. Alden's
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 June 1
    The Office: walked to Depot with Tom, Joe, and James Rowland; [John W.] Sexton; a matter concerning Sallie Cooke and "the club"; Laura in Gibraltar
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 June 4
    Ogontz: croquet club assembled for games then discussion of the proceedings of the business meeting in the parlor; George Thomas; Mr. and Mrs. George C. Thomas, Jr., Mr. and Mrs. Henry Butcher, Mr. and Mrs. Jay Cooke, Jr. all new members; Miss Rowland; Mr. Bingham
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Aug 10
    Ogontz "The end room": Nennie, James Rowland, Miss Henderson; description of "poney carriage" ride -- to J. B. Moorhead, Addie Thomas, Mrs. Wright, Shoemakertown; played backgammon
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Aug 13
    Ogontz "Library": Nennie, Mrs. Bingham, Mr. Pollard; rode in the "Germantown"; George and Ida Thomas, Miss Warwick, Tom Parvin; trip on Saturday with Ginnie and Caddie Moorhead, the Horstmans and their cousin Miss Mary, Charlie Sharpless; [Sandusky] dance, waltz, gallopade; Jenny Rowland, Clara Horstman, Caddie Rowland played piano; Sallie Cooke; sleeve buttons to Caldwells; Mr. Bingham
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Aug 14
    Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: carriage ride to "Bloomfield," Limekein turnpike beyond Waverly Heights, to the York Road, with John, Ida, Ginnie, and Nennie; George Thomas; Harry; Mr. Hawkins of the macadamized Chapel; sleeve buttoms from Caldwells; Mr. Brazier of Caldwells
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Aug 20
    Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: Mrs. Alden; met Mr. Evans, insurance agent who knew Mr. Bingham; Sallie Cooke; George Thomas
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Aug 21
    Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: Washington Gilpin, Jay and Joe Shoemaker; [Jay Cooke]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Sep 25
    Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: [George C.] Thomas; Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; played billiards; Clara; plan for the wedding; Joe Shoemaker, Charlie Dunn; Charlie Dennis [Note: Charles B. Dennis (uncle?)]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Sep 26
    Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; invitation to tea with Mrs. Brock, Charlie Dennis, and others
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Sep 27
    Ogontz "Library": Jay [Cooke, Jr.], Emma Ferris, Lollie Thomas, Minnie Parvin, Joe Shoemaker rode from church in the "Omnibuss"; discussion of Sunday School and Mr. Boulton preaching; Lake Mills; elaborate dinner menu; walk around grounds to stable, mausoleum, greenhouses, the old mill; saw Joe and Jay Shoemaker, Minnie Parvins, Lollie Thomas; Mrs. Brock's tea; Miss Warwick after church; Joe Shoemaker playing the organ
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Sep 28
    "The Cedars": Mr. Shoemaker, Joe and Bennie's house, the Cooke's old home where Laura spent her childhood; Mr. [George C.] Thomas, George [Thomas]; [John W.] Sexton; Joe [Shoemaker?]; visit to Ogontz; met Miss Warwick, James Rowland, Tom [Parvin] and Charlie Parvin on the train
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Sep 30
    Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: Mary Horstman, Mrs. Jacobs, Mrs. Wright, Charlie, Louise all at Ogontz along with George, Addie, Ginnie, Jay Cooke, Jr., and visitors Horace Lippincott and Mr. Hart; orchestra and playing billiards
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Sep 30
    Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: family matter concerning his mother, Mrs. Barney, and Laura; advises her to hear Dr. Keiffer
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 1
    Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: busy in office, [John W.] Sexton
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 2
    Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: loving thoughts, missing her; Philadelphia "is thronged with people -- 'the boys in blue' & others who have come to see the doings -- the Parade this afternoon was very fine & it took over two hours for the procession to pass the office -- to night they parade again -- then there will be speeches -- fireworks -- illuminations -- rows -- music & everything interesting..."; matter concerning his mother and her second marriage [to Dr. Keiffer]; death of baby Maggie Fahnestock; Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; sent black silk dress; visit to Ogontz
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 4
    Ogontz "The Chinese room": studying Sunday school lesson; Clara, Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; reference to "Friday was the great day of the 'Boys in blue'" -- his own account of some of the activities of October 2nd; their upcoming marriage; Dr. Newton's tale of the doings of his party at Gibraltar -- 'the trial,' 'the convention' or 'their celebration'; Dr. Newton's sermon, church; his mother and Dr. K[eiffer]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 7
    Ogontz: Jay [Cooke, Jr.], Clara; conservatory; Tom Parvin
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 8
    Ogontz: Clara, Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; playing baseball; hearing orchestrion; Charlie Parvin; dinner menu; playing football; Tom [Parvin]; going to Jenkintown for a political meeting in the hay wagon; invitation to "Bloomfield," the Thomas home
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 8
    Bloomfield: to Jenkintown to the political meeting in the hay wagon; Harry Birchall, Mary Bigar, Tom [Parvin], Bob [Parvin], Charlie Parvin, Charlie Dunn; Caddie Rowland; Harry Howe in "the procession of torch lighter bearers otherwise -- 'the Invincibles'" & also Harry Rodgers; Miss Carr; Lollie Thomas, Mary McKee, and Mrs. Tillis
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke [1868 Oct 9?]
    Annie Warwick, James Rowland; [John W.] Sexton, Jay [Cooke, Jr.]; playing billiards
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 10
    Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: asks result of her talk with her father [Jay Cooke]; Mr. [George C.] Thomas; Mrs. Appleton; Joe S[hoemaker] now choir leader
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 11
    The Parsonage: Mr. and Mrs. Appleton; Miss Boulton; describes curiosities collected by Appletons, including inkhorn, brass lamp, items from Palestine; Will Moorhead; Appleton's servants -- little "Kattie" who reminds him of 'the Marchioness' in 'The old curiosity shop'; Mr. Atkinson preached eloquently and beautifully and taught her father's [Jay Cooke] Bible class; Sunday School; the Cookes' feelings toward their daughter Laura's impending marriage to Charlie; death of Mrs. Brock's brother in Haiti by yellow fever; Clara, Jay [Cooke, Jr.]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 12
    Ogontz: Jay [Cooke, Jr.] and Clara; the Rowlands, Miss Carr, Tom Parvin, Joe Shoemaker; her father's [Jay Cooke] blessing on their marriage; Caddie [Rowland?]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 13
    Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: Mr. Bingham, [John W.] Sexton; card from his mother and the wedding cards of the new Mrs. Charles Hubbard of Sandusky, Ohio
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1868 Oct 14
    Office of Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: looking forward to being married in the spring; her black silk dress admired; love poems of Sir Phillip Sidney; tea at Elwell's; Clara's new house
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1869 Feb 26
    Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: played two games of billiards with Harry; [Jay Cooke] meeting with Mr. Wikeson in the Library at Ogontz; [Dorothea Allen Cooke], Nennie, Mr. [George C.] Thomas; playing backgammon; boxes of laces and trimmings for Laura's bridal dress; doing well in the office; Willie Newton
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1869 Mar 1
    Jay Cooke & Co. Bankers, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: work day discouraging
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke [1869 Mar]
    1622 Spruce Street: James Bingham and Chet Moss at the Continental; [John W.] Sexton and settling cash at the office; Harry Delaney; three yards of silk from Mr. Thomas' store; W[illia]m [White] Harding (1830- 1889), publisher of the Philadelphia Inquirer, at the office inquiring for Jay [Cooke, Jr.] and [Jay Cooke] -- rumor of Jay Cooke's being telegraphed to go to Washington, D. C. to see about accepting the Secretary of the Treasury; Laura attending the inauguration of President [Ulysses S. Grant]. [Note: Hugh McCulloch was the Secretary of Treasury until March 1869; Ulysses S. Grant was inaugurated on March 4, 1869]
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1871 Oct 8
    Chicago, Illinois: letter to his wife and five-month-old daughter; [J. B. T.] Marsh, Mr. Turner's brother-in-law in Branchtown to make the address to their S[unday] S[chool]; working in the offices of The Advance; dinner at the 'Palmer'; driving all over the city in a carriage; going to the city on the city cars -- went on the West Side to hear Robert Colyer, impressive services, and interesting sermon; describes church; visit to two Sunday Schools -- met Mrs. Bush, Mr. L. M. Brook's little sister; Edward M. Davis, [Jay Cooke], J. Alfred Townsend, and C.T.C.
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1871 Oct 9
    [Letterhead of] Editorial Rooms of The Advance, Chicago, Illinois: description of the great fire which destroyed Chicago; city half in flames -- courthouse burnt to ground; walked to see fire, stopped at 'Palmer House'; office of the Advance Company totally destroyed; Mrs. Turner's house on Wabash Avenue burned down; the Post Office in flames and destroyed as well as nearly all the prominent buildings -- the Fremont Hotel, the Union Central Depot, the 'Palmer House,' Robert Colyer's magnificent church; "poor women...with nothing in the world left of ruined men, homes & business..." and "the hundreds of thieves walking off with their plunder in their hands or arms..."; requests the raising of funds
  - Charles D. Barney to Laura E. Cooke 1875 Aug 3